Guide to the Yale Religion in Higher Education Program Records
Yale University Divinity School Library
Yale Religion in Higher Education Program Records
1928-1966
1946-1966
RG 182
Yale University Divinity School Library
6.5
(16 boxes)
These records relate to the Religion in Higher Education program at Yale. Yale was an important center for Masters and Doctoral level studies in this field during the mid- twentieth century.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Deposited in the Library in the 1960s
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
Clarence Prouty Shedd was among the first notable figures in Yale's emphasis on religion in higher education. Shedd was appointed Lecturer on Student Work in 1923 and was a fellow of National Council of Religion in Higher Education. He went on to become the Stephen Merrell Clement Professor of Christian Methods at Yale Divinity School until his retirement in 1955. Arriving at Yale in 1955 was J. Edward Dirks, who was Associate Professor Religion in Higher Education from 1955 to 1958 and Stephen Merrell Clement Professor of Christian Methods from 1958 to 1967. Dirks was also on loan from Yale as Secretary of the University Commission of the World's Student Christian Federation. He served as Editor of The Christian Scholar and as Chairman of the Executive Committee of the Faculty Christian Fellowship. The Religion in Higher Education Program at Yale was most active during the 1940s through 1960s.
Scope and Contents
Though fragmentary and of uncertain provenance, this collection provides valuable documentation of the Religion in Higher Education program at Yale, primarily from the 1920s through 1966. The files were found in a YDS basement storage area and it is not entirely clear whether they were all from one source.
Series I is designated at J.Edward Dirks Files and contains documentation relating both to his work at Yale and as Secretary of the University Commission of the World Student Christian Federation. There are also J. Edward Dirks papers in YDSL Record Group No. 30, Miscellaneous Personal Papers Collection. Series II, Course Materials, covers the era when Clarence Shedd was the primary faculty member at YDS in the area of religion in higher education. An additional 36 linear feet of Clarence Prouty Shedds Papers are found in YDSL Record Group No. 35. The Resource Materials in Series III date from both the Shedd and Dirks eras. They were most likely from a central file in the Yale office of the religion in higher education program.
In addition to their relation to other papers of Dirks and Shedd, these records relate to several other collections at the Yale Divinity Library, including the Archives of the World Student Christian Federation (YDSL RG 46); the Archives of The Danforth Study of Campus Ministries (YDSL RG 62), which was based at YDS and directed by Kenneth Underwood 1962-1966, the Archives of the Religious Education Association (YDSL RG 74), the Archives of the National Association of College and University Chaplains and Directors of Religious Life (YDSL RG 167), as well as the records of various iterations of the North American student Christian movement.
Arrangement
Series I, J. Edward Dirks Files, 1946-1966
Series II, Course Materials, 1929-1962
Series III, Resource Files, 1928-1966
Universities and colleges -- Religion; Shedd, Clarence Prouty, 1887-; Dirks, John Edward, 1919-; Yale University. Divinity School
- J. Edward Dirks Files, 1946-1966; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  Additional J. Edward Dirks papers are available in YDSL Record Group No. 30, Miscellaneous Personal Papers Collection.
  - Correspondence
    - Yale University, 1946-1965 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Asia trip, 1949-1956 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - University Teachers' Commission, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Maury, Philippe, 1954-1965 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Miscellaneous, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Re. Hazen grant, 1955-1960 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - World Student Christian Federation, 1955-1966 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Re. reprinting of grey book, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Miscellaneous, 1959-1960 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Faculty Christian Fellowship, 1963-1965 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Conferences
    - National Council on Religion in Higher Education, 1954-1962 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - WSCF Leaders in India, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - World Student Christian Federation, 1955-1956 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - University Commission Consultation, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - "The Meaning of the Secular", 1958 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Religion in Higher Education, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - National Council of United Campus Christian Fellowship, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - United Campus Christian Fellowship, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - World Student Christian Federation, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Literature
    - Miscellaneous, 1952-1956 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Latin America, 1958-1959 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - "Ministry to the Campus", 1961 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Miscellaneous, 1964-1966 (Box 3, Folder 23)
      - Reports
    - University Commission, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Travel in Latin America and Asia, 1956-1959 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - University Teachers' Commission
    - Correspondence, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Meetings, 1954, 1955, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 27-29)
    - Literature and related correspondence, 1956-1959 (Box 3, Folder 30)
- Course Materials, 1929-1962; Series II
  See also the Clarence Prouty Shedd Papers, YDSL Record Group No. 35 for related material.
  - Research studies
    - "Weigle Study" - Ministry candidates, 1929 (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - "Religious Studies in Colleges", 1929-1935 (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - "College Work among Episcopalians", 1933-1947 (Box 4, Folder 33-35)
    - "YMCA and College Christian Movements", 1940 (Box 4, Folder 36)
    - "Post-war Plans for Religious Studies at Yale": correspondence of Sidney Lovett, 1944-1945 (Box 5, Folder 37)
    - "United Student Christian Council Study Committee": miscellaneous studies, 1944-1951 (Box 5, Folder 38)
    - "Cooperation of Protestant Campus Religious Organizations": questionnaires, 1946 (Box 5, Folder 39)
    - "The Role of Religion in the Urban University", 1946 (Box 5, Folder 40-41)
    - "Religious Centers for Student Work: A Yale Study", 1947 (Box 6, Folder 42)
    - "Religious Attitudes Survey", 1947-1948 (Box 6, Folder 43)
    - "Courses in Religion at Various Colleges", 1950 (Box 6, Folder 44)
    - "Training Courses for Student Religious Workers": Yale University, 1950-1951 (Box 6, Folder 45)
    - "Leadership Qualities for a YMCA Secretary": correspondence, 1950-1951 (Box 6, Folder 46)
    - Miscellaneous studies, 1951 (Box 6, Folder 47)
    - "The Comparative Orthodoxy of Freshmen and Seniors", 1953 (Box 6, Folder 48)
    - "Rockefeller Fellows at Yale", 1958-1962 (Box 6, Folder 49)
  - Yale "Religion in Higher Education" course
    - Collected student reports, 1945-1946 (Box 6, Folder 50)
    - Term paper topics, 1948 (Box 6, Folder 51)
    - Student reports: Cates, William, 1948 (Box 6, Folder 52)
    - Student reports: Herman, Alan, 1948 (Box 6, Folder 53)
    - Student reports: Porter, Joe, 1948 (Box 6, Folder 54)
    - Collected student reports, late 1940s (Box 6, Folder 55)
    - Course documents, 1954 (Box 7, Folder 56)
    - Collected student reports, 1956-1957 (Box 7, Folder 57-60)
- Resource Files, 1928-1966; Series III
  - Yale University
    - Dwight hall records, 1928-1960 (Box 8, Folder 61)
    - Wesley Foundation: reports and literature, 1938-1957 (Box 8, Folder 62)
    - Yale Christian Association: literature, 1943 (Box 8, Folder 63)
    - Westminster Fellowship, 1947-1948 (Box 8, Folder 64)
    - Inter-church Council, 1947-1949 (Box 8, Folder 65)
    - Yale Consultation on Religion in Higher Education, 1953 (Box 8, Folder 66)
    - News items, 1961 (Box 8, Folder 67)
  - Faculty Christian Fellowship
    - General records, 1951-1961 (Box 8, Folder 68)
    - Conferences, 1952-1953 (Box 8, Folder 69-70)
    - Literature: "Faculty Forum", 1957-1965 (Box 8, Folder 71)
    - University Christian Mission, 1951-1952 (Box 8, Folder 72)
    - "Work with Faculty", 1951 (Box 8, Folder 73)
  - National Council of the Churches of Christ
    - Annual reports, 1948-1960 (Box 9, Folder 74)
    - Conferences, 1957-1958 (Box 9, Folder 75)
    - Literature: Commission on Higher Education, 1952-1966 (Box 9, Folder 76-77)
    - Department of Campus Christian Life, 1951-1953 (Box 9, Folder 78)
    - Department of Ecumenical Relations, 1951 (Box 9, Folder 79)
    - Department of the Ministry, 1957-1960 (Box 9, Folder 80)
    - Division of Christian Education, 1955-1958 (Box 9, Folder 81)
    - Interseminary Movement, 1947-1957 (Box 9, Folder 82)
    - Miscellaneous records, 1963 (Box 9, Folder 83)
    - General records, 1953-1964 (Box 10, Folder 84)
    - Committee for the Interseminary Movement, 1963-1964 (Box 10, Folder 85)
  - Student Christian Movement
    - Conferences, 1937-1965 (Box 10, Folder 86)
    - Literature, 1945-1956 (Box 10, Folder 87-88)
    - Middle Atlantic Region records, 1957 (Box 10, Folder 89)
    - New England Region records, 1943-1960 (Box 10, Folder 90)
    - "Christian Student Foundation", 1950 (Box 10, Folder 91)
    - Collected materials on student religious attitudes, 1933-1951 (Box 10, Folder 92)
    - College Church Study, 1957 (Box 11, Folder 93)
    - Local programs, no date (Box 11, Folder 94)
    - Merger proposal, 1956-1960 (Box 11, Folder 95)
    - Seminary programs, 1954-1955 (Box 11, Folder 96)
    - "The Present Task of the SCM", 1945 (Box 11, Folder 97)
    - International: Britain, 1952-1963 (Box 11, Folder 98)
    - International: Burma, 1952 (Box 11, Folder 99)
    - International: Canada, 1963-1964 (Box 11, Folder 100)
    - International: Ceylon, 1955-1957 (Box 11, Folder 101)
    - International: England, 1953-1964 (Box 11, Folder 102)
    - International: France, 1957-1959 (Box 11, Folder 103)
    - International: Germany, 1957 (Box 11, Folder 104)
    - International: Holland, 1953 (Box 11, Folder 105)
    - International: Hungary, no date (Box 11, Folder 106)
    - International: India, 1943-1967 (Box 11, Folder 107)
    - International: India - reports of J. E. Dirks, 1961 (Box 11, Folder 108)
    - International: India - printed material, 1962-1966 (Box 11, Folder 109)
    - International: Indonesia, 1965 (Box 11, Folder 110)
    - International: Japan, 1954 (Box 12, Folder 111)
    - International: Latin America, 1955-1963 (Box 12, Folder 112)
    - International: Lebanon, 1955-1962 (Box 12, Folder 113)
    - International: Norway, Sweeden, Denmark, 1959 (Box 12, Folder 114)
    - International: Phillipines, 1956 (Box 12, Folder 115)
    - International: Puerto Rico, 1964-1965 (Box 12, Folder 116)
    - International: South Africa, 1958 (Box 12, Folder 117)
    - International: Syria, 1955 (Box 12, Folder 118)
    - International: Thailand, 1951 (Box 12, Folder 119)
  - UCCF National Council
    - Miscellaneous records, 1963-1964 (Box 12, Folder 120)
  - University Christian Mission
    - Printed materials and reports, 1946-1955 (Box 12, Folder 121)
    - Printed material: "Religion in Life Week", 1955-1957 (Box 12, Folder 122)
    - Printed materials and reports, 1957-1961 (Box 12, Folder 123)
  - United Student Christian Council
    - Correspondence, 1944-1946 (Box 13, Folder 124)
    - Literature and publications, 1945-1966 (Box 13, Folder 125)
    - Re. literature and publications, 1962-1964 (Box 13, Folder 126)
    - Structure reports, 1940-1949 (Box 13, Folder 127)
    - Structure reports: Executive Committee, 1944-1957 (Box 13, Folder 128)
    - Meeting report, 1946 (Box 13, Folder 129)
    - Meeting report, 1947 (Box 13, Folder 130)
    - Meeting report, 1948 (Box 13, Folder 131)
    - Meeting report, 1949 (Box 13, Folder 132)
    - Meeting report, 1950 (Box 13, Folder 133)
    - Meeting report, 1951 (Box 13, Folder 134)
    - Meeting report, 1952 (Box 13, Folder 135)
    - Kalmazoo Proposal, 1952 (Box 14, Folder 136)
    - Meeting report, 1953 (Box 14, Folder 137)
    - Meeting report, 1957 (Box 14, Folder 138)
    - Meeting report, 1958 (Box 14, Folder 139)
    - Committe on Religion in Higher Education, 1945-1949 (Box 14, Folder 140)
    - Campus Strategy Committee, 1946-1950 (Box 14, Folder 141)
    - Committee on University Work, 1944-1951 (Box 14, Folder 142)
    - Denison Consultation, 1944-1945 (Box 14, Folder 143)
    - World Student Christian Federation literature, 1946-1952 (Box 14, Folder 144)
    - Whitby documents and SCM work, 1948-1950 (Box 14, Folder 145)
    - Personnel Committee reports and studies, 1949-1950 (Box 14, Folder 146)
    - Ecumenical Student Workers Conference, 1953 (Box 14, Folder 147)
    - Study Department report, 1957 (Box 14, Folder 148)
    - "Life and Mission of the Church" materials, 1958 (Box 14, Folder 149)
    - Merger proposal, 1958 (Box 14, Folder 150)
    - Universal Day of Prayer, 1958-1959 (Box 14, Folder 151)
    - Description of Christian movements, 1958-1961 (Box 14, Folder 152)
    - Relationships: American Council on Education, 1957-1962 (Box 14, Folder 153)
    - Relationships: American Philosophical Association, 1957 (Box 14, Folder 154)
    - Relationships: Association for the Coordination of University Religious Affairs, 1960-1964 (Box 14, Folder 155)
    - Relationships: Association for Higher Education, 1961-1963 (Box 14, Folder 156)
    - Relationships: Council for Religion in Independent Schools, Inc., 1962-1965 (Box 14, Folder 157)
    - Relationships: Ecumenical Movement, 1958 (Box 15, Folder 158)
    - Relationships: fraternities, 1957 (Box 15, Folder 159)
    - Relationships: local student Christian groups, 1942-1950 (Box 15, Folder 160)
    - Relationships: National Association of College and University Chaplains, 1958-1964 (Box 15, Folder 161)
    - Relationships: National Council of the Churches of Christ, 1938-1952 (Box 15, Folder 162)
    - Relationships: New England Board of Higher Education, 1957-1962 (Box 15, Folder 163)
    - Relationships: student groups (re. race relations), no date (Box 15, Folder 164)
    - Relationships: Society for Religion in Higher Education, 1963 (Box 15, Folder 165)
    - Relationships: Trustees of Church-related colleges, 1954-1965 (Box 15, Folder 166)
    - Relationships: United States National Student Association, 1961 (Box 15, Folder 167)
    - Relationships: World Council of Churches, 1950-1954 (Box 15, Folder 168)
    - Relationships: World Student Christian Federation Committee, 1945-1951 (Box 15, Folder 169)
    - Relationships: World Student Christian Federation - United Student Christian Council history, 1944-1952 (Box 15, Folder 170)
  - Topical files
    - "Christianity and Political Action", 1951-1958 (Box 16, Folder 171)
    - "Christianity and the Fine Arts", 1951-1958 (Box 16, Folder 172)
    - "Higher Education Information", 1945-1952 (Box 16, Folder 173)
    - "International Affairs and Student Christian Movements", 1946-1956 (Box 16, Folder 174)
    - "Racial Integration", 1952-1957 (Box 16, Folder 175)
    - "Racial Segregation in Schools", 1955-1956 (Box 16, Folder 176)